<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="wayland_tablet">

  <copyright>
    Copyright 2014 © Stephen "Lyude" Chandler Paul

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="wl_tablet_manager" version="1">
    <description summary="controller object for graphic tablet devices">
      An object that provides access to the graphics tablets available on this
      system.
    </description>

    <enum name="tablet_type">
      <description summary="tablet type">
	Describes the type of tablet
      </description>

      <entry name="external" value="0" summary="The tablet is an external tablet, such as an Intuos"/>
      <entry name="internal" value="1" summary="The tablet is a built-in tablet, usually in a laptop"/>
      <entry name="display" value="2" summary="The tablet is a display tablet, such as a Cintiq"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="device_added">
      <description summary="new device notification"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wl_tablet" summary="the newly added graphics tablet"/>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="the device name"/>
      <arg name="vid" type="uint" summary="vendor id"/>
      <arg name="pid" type="uint" summary="product id"/>
      <arg name="type" type="uint"/>
    </event>

    <event name="tool_added">
      <description summary="a new tool has been used with a tablet">
	This event is sent whenever a tool that has not previously been used
	with a tablet comes into use. This provides the information about the
	tool, along with a wl_tablet_tool object that is unique to this tool.
	If the tablet the tool is being used with does not report the serial
	numbers for each tool, then the uniqueness of each tool object cannot
	be guaranteed. On tablets where the serial number is not reported, the
	"tool_serial" argument will always be 0.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wl_tablet_tool" summary="the newly added tablet tool"/>
      <arg name="tablet" type="object" interface="wl_tablet" summary="The tablet that the tool was seen with"/>
      <arg name="tool_type" type="uint" summary="the physical tool type"/>
      <arg name="tool_serial" type="uint" summary="the unique serial number of the tool"/>
      <arg name="extra_axes" type="uint" summary="A bitfield of all of the extra axes the tablet supports"/>
    </event>

    <event name="seat">
      <description summary="the seat associated with the tablet manager">
	For various functions with the weston desktop shell, a input seat of
	some sort is required. Because tablets are not officially part of the
	wayland protocol yet, we can't grab the tablet manager resource from
	the seat like we would a pointer or a touchscreen. Therefore, an event
	must be sent that contains a pointer to the wl_seat object that the
	client is using that is associated with the tablet manager.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="The wl_seat object for the tablet manager"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wl_tablet_tool" version="1">
    <description summary="a physical tablet tool">
      An unique object that represents a physical tool that has been, or is
      currently in use with a tablet connected to the system. Each
      wl_tablet_tool object stays valid until the client releases it, and the
      compositor will always reuse the wl_tablet_tool object (if it still
      exists) to indicate that the object's respective physical tool has come
      into proximity of a tablet again.

      It should be noted that each wl_tablet_tool object's uniqueness depends on
      the tablet's ability to report serial numbers. If the tablet doesn't
      support this capability, then the tool cannot be guaranteed to be unique.
    </description>

    <enum name="type">
      <description summary="a physical tool type">
	Describes the physical type of a tool.
      </description>
      <entry name="pen" value="0x140" summary="Pen"/>
      <entry name="eraser" value="0x141" summary="Eraser"/>
      <entry name="brush" value="0x142" summary="Brush"/>
      <entry name="pencil" value="0x143" summary="Pencil"/>
      <entry name="airbrush" value="0x144" summary="Airbrush"/>
      <entry name="finger" value="0x145" summary="Finger"/>
      <entry name="mouse" value="0x146" summary="Mouse"/>
      <entry name="lens" value="0x147" summary="Lens"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="axis_flag">
      <description summary="a group of additional axes for a tablet">
	Describes a group of additional axes on a tablet.
      </description>
      <entry name="tilt" value="1" summary="Tilt axes"/>
      <entry name="pressure" value="2" summary="Pressure axis"/>
      <entry name="distance" value="4" summary="Distance axis"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="removed">
      <description summary="tool removed">
	This event is sent when the tool is removed from the system. The client
	should not expect the resource it currently has associated with the
	tool to be used again if the tool comes back into proximity later.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="release" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the memory for the tool object">
	This destroys the client's resource for this tool object. If the tool
	comes back into proximity, a new resource will be created for the
	client and associated with the tool.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wl_tablet" version="1">
    <description summary="drawing tablet device">
      The wl_tablet interface represents one drawing tablet device.

      The wl_tablet interface generates axis events, enter, and leave events for
      the surfaces that the tool is held over and button events for the buttons
      on a tablet tool.
    </description>

    <enum name="button_state">
      <description summary="physical button state">
	Describes the physical state of a button which provoked the button event
      </description>
      <entry name="released" value="0" summary="button is not pressed"/>
      <entry name="pressed" value="1" summary="button is pressed"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="proximity_in">
      <description summary="proximity in event">
	Notification that this tablet's tool is focused on a certain surface.

	This event can be received when the tool has moved from one surface to
	another, or when the tool has come back into proximity.
      </description>

      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
      <arg name="tool" type="object" interface="wl_tablet_tool" summary="The tool that came into proximity"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface" summary="The current surface the tablet tool is over"/>
    </event>

    <event name="proximity_out">
      <description summary="proximity out event">
	Notification that this tablet's tool has either left proximity, or is no
	longer focused on a certain surface.

	In addition, when the tablet tool leaves proximity of the tablet, a set
	of button release events will be sent for each button that was held
	down on the tablet. If the tool stays within proximity of the tablet,
	but the focus changes from one surface to another, a button release
	event will not be sent until the button is actually released or the
	tool leaves the proximity of the tablet.
      </description>

      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
    </event>

    <event name="motion">
      <description summary="motion event">
	Sent whenever a tablet tool moves.
      </description>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
      <arg name="x" type="fixed" summary="surface-relative x coordinate"/>
      <arg name="y" type="fixed" summary="surface-relative y coordinate"/>
    </event>

    <event name="down">
      <description summary="tablet tool is making contact">
	Sent whenever the tablet tool comes in contact with the surface of the
	tablet. If the tablet tool moves out of a region while in contact with
	the surface of the tablet, the client owning said region will receive a
	wl_tablet::up event, followed by a wl_tablet::proximity_out event and a
	wl_tablet::frame event.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
    </event>

    <event name="up">
      <description summary="tablet tool is no longer making contact">
	Sent whenever the tablet tool stops making contact with the surface of
	the tablet, or when the tablet tool moves off of a surface while it was
	making contact with the tablet's surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
    </event>

    <event name="pressure">
      <description summary="pressure change event">
	Sent whenever the pressure axis on a tool changes. The value of this
	event is normalized to a value between 0 and 65535.
      </description>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
      <arg name="pressure" type="fixed" summary="The current pressure value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="distance">
      <description summary="distance change event">
	Sent whenever the distance axis on a tool changes. The value of this
	event is normalized to a value between 0 and 65535.
      </description>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
      <arg name="distance" type="fixed" summary="The current distance value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="tilt">
      <description summary="tilt change event">
	Sent whenever one or both of the tilt axes on a tool change. Each tilt
	value is normalized between -65535 and 65535.
      </description>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
      <arg name="tilt_x" type="fixed" summary="The current value of the X tilt axis"/>
      <arg name="tilt_y" type="fixed" summary="The current value of the Y tilt axis"/>
    </event>

    <event name="button">
      <description summary="button event">
	Sent whenever a button on the stylus is pressed or released.
      </description>

      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="The time of the event with millisecond granularity"/>
      <arg name="button" type="uint" summary="The button whose state has changed"/>
      <arg name="state" type="uint" summary="Whether the button was pressed or released"/>
    </event>

    <event name="frame">
      <description summary="frame event">
	Marks the end of a series of axis updates from the tablet. Motion,
	pressure, distance, and tilt events are all axis events. Axis updates
	are received from drawing tablets at the same time, so the frame event
	may be used to separate each individual series of axis updates.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="removed">
      <description summary="tablet removed event">
	Sent when the tablet has been removed from the system. The behavior of
	the wl_tablet_tool objects afterwards depends on the type of the
	tablet. For tablets where serial numbers are reported, the tools will
	be kept in memory until there are no other tablets which support serial
	numbers connected to the system. If the tool object is one that lacks a
	serial number because it originated from a tablet where serial numbers
	are not reported, then it will be destroyed if the tablet it belongs to
	is destroyed.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="release" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the tablet object"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_cursor">
      <description summary="set the tablet tool's surface">
	Sets the surface of the pointer used for the tablet's tool object. This
	surface is only shown when the tool is in proximity of the tablet. If
	the surface is NULL, the pointer image is hidden completely.

	The parameters hotspot_x and hotspot_y define the position of the
	pointer surface relative to the pointer location. Its top-left corner
	is always at (x, y) - (hotspot_x, hotspot_y), where (x, y) are the
	coordinates of the pointer location, in surface local coordinates.

	On surface.attach requests to the pointer surface, hotspot_x and
	hotspot_y are decremented by the x and y parameters passed to the
	request. Attach must be confirmed by wl_surface.commit as usual.

	The hotspot can also be updated by passing the currently set pointer
	surface to this request with new values for hotspot_x and hotspot_y.

	The current and pending input regions of the wl_surface are cleared,
	and wl_surface.set_input_region is ignored until the wl_surface is no
	longer used as the cursor. When the use as a cursor ends, the current
	and pending input regions become undefined, and the wl_surface is
	unmapped.
      </description>

      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of the enter event"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface" allow-null="true"/>
      <arg name="hotspot_x" type="int" summary="x coordinate in surface-relative coordinates"/>
      <arg name="hotspot_y" type="int" summary="y coordinate in surface-relative coordinates"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
